Go!
Comrades. Go!
Nothing.
There's nothing too.
Ahh!
It's a trap!
Take cover!
Comrade Fah, take everyone to
the edge of the forest.
Ouch!
Hurry!
I'll provide cover while you move.
Get back, Comrade.
Hey! Comrade.
Comrade! Damn!
Argh!
Comrade Fah, hurry up!
Go.
Argh!
Comrade Fah, how's it going?
I'm OK.
Take our comrades safely back to the base.
No, I'll go with Comrade Ploeng.
Go!
Stick to our ideology,
Get back, Comrade.
Ouch!
Follow them. I'll take care of this.
Go!
Argh!
"When Light Fades" (Episode 5)
Why haven't they returned yet?
They're back.
Our comrades-in-arms are back.
Let's take care of the
wounded comrades. Quick!
Comrade Yue.
Bai Tong.
Bai Tong, calm down.
Where's my dad?
Calm down.
Bai Tong, calm down.
Where's Comrade Ploeng?
Dad... Dad!
Bai Tong, please no.
Where's Comrade Ploeng?
I'll take you there.
- Let me go.
- Bai Tong.
I'll rescue my dad.
I'll go too.
Stay here. Don't mess around.
It's OK, Bai Tong. Relax.
Listen to me, Bai Tong.
Comrade Ploeng, Comrade Ploeng...
Comrade Ploeng.
Dad!
Bai Tong.
Bai Tong, calm down.
Dad!
I want to see my dad.
Bai Tong.
Bai Tong, calm down.
No, I want to see my dad.
Bai Tong, please calm down.
It's OK, Bai Tong.
Bai Tong, calm down.
No, no!
Bai Tong, listen to me.
I want to see my dad.
Bai Tong, please calm down.
You told me you would
take me out of the forest.
Why did you leave me alone like this?
Am I beautiful, dad?
Oh!
Ha ha.
Yes, you really are.
You know...
I and all comrades are tasked
with protecting the base.
To make everyone in
the base safe and sound.
If we win the battle,
we won't have to hold guns any longer.
Dad, let's win the battle,
and take me out of here.
Ha ha.
Yes maam, my girl.
We don't need to win.
Just bring my dad back—that's enough.
You once said,
you don't like the battle-
-because it's brutal.
But what's even more brutal-
-is what comes after.
Every time we finnish the battle,
Comrade Ploeng...
Comrade Ploeng would
take me to the battlefield...
to bring all the bodies back to the base.
Comrade Ploeng taught me...
we need to bring everyone...
to go back to the base no matter what.
It was supposed to be me.
I was supposed to go
instead of Comrade Ploeng.
So Comrade Bai Tong
wouldn't be left alone like this.
What about me?
How can I live if you died?
With me,
you can feel free to cry.
It was supposed to be me.
I'm sorry, Comrade Ploeng.
I didn't mean for this to happen.
I'm sorry.
You're so cruel.
Do you know...
Comrade Ploeng's daughter
lost her mom when she was born.
Now she's lost her dad.
How can she live?
I didn't want to do it.
It's a duty.
I'm sorry.
Ouch!
There's a traitor in our base.
Otherwise, there's no way-
-they could've known
our battle plan in advance.
Who do you suspect?
Any update on Yaguar, who I had you follow?
How can Yaguar be a traitor?
He's so naive.
He's been acting strange recently.
Like he has a secret.
People who look innocent like this...
are the real danger.
Untrustworthy.
Especially the student comrades.
Why are we suspecting each other?
We can't trust anybody now.
If you find anything, report it at once.
Report Comrade Ploeng's
situation to the main base.
So they can appoint a new leader.
Comrade Ploeng died less than a day ago.
You want to talk about
a new leader already?
Sooner or later there
will be a new leader, right?
Why drag it out?
Comrade Bai Tong has
been crying since morning.
She has stayed all day,
Comrade Ploeng is never really gone.
If you miss Comrade Ploeng,
he's always in your heart.
If Comrade Ploeng
saw you crying like this,
he'd be very worried, right?
Dad doesn't like me to cry.
Being Comrade Ploeng's
daughter, I should not cry.
Be strong.
Very good.
Let's go eat.
Since I heard the gunshots,
I realized how close death really is.
Actually, I thought I had braced myself,
But when the incident with
Comrade Ploeng happened,
I couldn't keep myself together.
We never know when our turn will come.
Don't jinx it.
Life is short.
We never know if tomorrow will come.
You and Comrade Ying
seem to have something on your minds.
You should talk it out,
so you won't regret later.
Let me help you.
Don't.
Let's eat together.
I'll do the dishes too.
Why are you so strangely kind today?
Mada.
Let's get back together.
I didn't mean to hurt you back then.
I was really worried about you.
I broke up with you,
because I didn't like who I was
when I was with you.
Having me as your lover,
is it really that bad?
You did nothing wrong, Sila.
But we were too different.
We can take it slow and adjust.
Whatever you think or feel,
I'll try to understand.
No need.
I don't want to overthink.
I don't want to be sad.
I don't want to feel stupid again.
If we go back to being friends,
maybe it'll be better than this.
If we force it,
we'll hurt each other without meaning to.
Then we will hate each other.
I don't want to hate you.
Let's break up while we're still in love.
That's for the best.
So long, Comrade Gaun Hin.
If you can turn back time,
would you kill him?
I'd do the same.
I don't want you to die.
Among the Hmong,
they give cockscomb flowers
to someone they're interested in.
It means...
“I want to get to know you,”
“I want to talk to you.”
I gave it to you. I'm not taking it back.
How can I live if you died?
With me,
you can feel free to cry.
Life is short.
We never know if there's
a second chance tomorrow.
I'm heading out of the base.
Come with me, Comrade Saeng.
Do we have a mission?
No.
Isn't it against the rules-
-to go out without one?
Where are we going, Comrade Yue?
Somewhere.
There are some scary
legends about the area.
Ghosts?
Some people died there.
People die everywhere.
But if it becomes a legend,
it isn't just a normal death.
Years ago,
two male comrades were found to be in love.
So they took their own
lives at Chan Siao Cave.
It's not far from where we're going.
Over there.
Scared?
I just feel sad.
Comrade Yue, what
would you do if it were you?
I'd do anything to be with my love,
but in the end-
-if I must choose between love-
and his life...
I'll do everything to keep him alive.
Even I must sacrifice my own life.
Comrade Yue, wait for me.
Watch your step, follow my footsteps.
Are you OK?
I'm thirsty.
I'm really thirsty.
Can I drink your water?
Didn't you bring your own water?
You rushed me, so I
didn't have time to grab it.
So let's take a break here.
Better?
Wow!
So this is what it's like. It's so beautiful
it makes people forget how tired they are.
Woohoo!
When I joined the troop in my first year,
I was in a low mental state.
It's Comrade Ploeng who brought me here.
He told me to look down there.
He taught me that when
your problems feel too big,
if you step back a little,
they'll seem smaller.
Back then I was living aimlessly.
I volunteered for fighting.
Because I don't have
any family members left.
Comrade Ploeng told me...
If you don't care about yourself,
then find someone-
-you want to take care of.
Someone
you want to live your life for.
If you find that person,
bring them here.
So you brought me here.
I think you're my person.
My name is Ravin.
Ravin!
The soldiers might hear us.
You brought me a long way.
This place is beautiful.
Why don't you let yourself go a little?
Try not to worry about anything.
This is so damn fun!
My name is Sasin.
Sasin?
Is Sasin your name?
Aren't you afraid the
soldiers might hear it?
I just brought you up here.
There's nothing to be afraid of.
I will protect Ravin with my life.
So damn happy!
When will the people
from the main base go out again?
No one has been outside-
-since Comrade Ploeng died.
There's only Comrade Roong.
She brought medicine to the villagers.
Comrade Roong?
Who's Comrade Roong?
Comrade Roong is-
-the female leader in Saeng Dao Base.
She's the sister of Comrade Fah.
Any news?
Yaguar told me...
they are investigating
the traitor in the base,
and who shot Comrade Ploeng.
Yang Sue.
I have a task for you.
What are you sitting here thinking about?
I miss Comrade Ploeng.
This compass, Comrade Ploeng gave it to me.
He was like my father.
I was named by him.
Your name is Yue.
I've wanted to know for a long time.
What is the meaning of Yue?
Yue is a Chinese word.
It means the moon.
It's written like this.
And my name, Ravin.
It means the sun.
How do I write it?
Can you write it?
The sun.
It can be written in Chinese like this.
It pronounced as 'rì'
Rì.
Even though the sun and the moon...
are both in the sky,
they can't be next to each other.
What if...
I put the sun,
'rì,
right there.
And put Yue-
next to it like this.
Does it mean anything?
It does.
If we place “rì” (the sun)
and “Yue” (the moon) together.
The sun becomes smaller,
as if it's being embraced by the moon.
It read as 'Ming'.
Ming?
It means the light.
The light.
So the sun and the moon can be together.
And they shine bright for each other.
What's gotten into you?
You were just smiling a second ago.
Did I said something wrong?
I killed a person,
then fled into the forest.
How can I be your light?
But you didn't intend to do it.
It's still killing.
At first, I thought...
I wanted to kill him.
He's the reason my father died.
But in the end,
when he finally died
it made me hate myself.
I became
another bad person,
who killed someone else's father.
Don't think that way.
There's no need to blame yourself.
Just don't do it again.
I'm not good at comforting people,
but I want to comfort you.
Feel better?
Not yet.
Not yet?
What do I have to do?
Better.
Let's go wash up.
Go.
What are you doing?
If you're wet at night in the forest,
you could freeze to death.
You told me to go wash up.
If I don't go, how do I clean myself?
I'll wipe you down.
It'll be cleaner than taking a shower.
Hurt?
Not anymore.
What?
Why is your heart pounding?
That's enough wiping.
How is that enough?
You said it'll be cleaner
than taking a shower.
This is only the upper part.
The lower part is...
Why are you taking it off?
Wipe it for me, please.
Are you OK?
What if I'm not?
What should I do?
Do you feel cold?
Getting better?
You'll get warm soon.
You're naughty.
What would you do if I
were naughty and stubborn?
Stubborn kids get punished.
Are you scared?
Or do you want to stop?
If you want to keep
going, you can't stop now.
I'm yours.
And I'm yours.
Can I have your knife?
We just got together.
You're already trying to kill me?
Please.
Come on.
This tree will be our witness.
No matter what happens,
we will get through it together.
Why are you giving me a gun?
Do you want me to shoot now?
Look closely.
(Sasin Ngaochan.)
So you'll feel like I'm
always here with you.
I want you to always
be right by my side, too.
Here's mine.
Ravin Chaichan.
Hey! Do you know my last name?
Every student who fled to the forest,
Where they studied, what their names are...
I have all the information.
But you… I've remembered
since the first day.
You remember that well.
Did you have a crush on
me the first time we met?
When I first met you,
I thought you were-
-a mischievous kid.
What about now?
How do you feel?
This is how I feel.
What are you doing? I'm blushing.
Do you like it?
Time flies when we're happy.
I won't be able to be
near you when we go back.
Yes, you will, Vin.
What did you call me?
Your nickname is Vin, right?
I heard Comrade Gaun
Hin called you with that.
So you won't call me comrade?
Well... we are more than comrades now.
So do we have to call
each other something else?
And...
What are we now?
Alright, I'll stop teasing you.
What do you want me to call you?
Sin is OK.
Someone's here.
A patrol comrade said...
you left the base last night.
Where did you go?
We had some business.
What kind of business?
What's going on?
Comrade Saeng, you go on ahead to the base.
Yes sir.
So?
Yang Sue reported...
there's a rumor about Captain Dan Din
among the villagers.
Dan Din?
Word is, Dan Din's
been moving between
the base and the village,
where the villagers gather.
He's expected to come back again tomorrow.
How is the main base reacting?
We've reported it since the
day Comrade Ploeng died.
But they've never sent
any orders down here.
Good.
If he comes again,
I'll kill him.
If we kill the son of
a high-ranking soldier
outside the battlefield,
that would mean we're going
to war with the authorities.
One more thing,
There's no orders from the main base.
So we shouldn't act on our own.
The most important thing is...
to avenge Comrade Ploeng.
Whoever is a coward, stay here.
But I'll go.
I'll go with you.
Comrade Yue.
Comrade Yue, are you there?
Yes, I am.
I brought you some food.
What are you doing? Working?
Nope.
I'd better not bother you.
I'll go on the mission with
Comrade Fah tomorrow.
You stay here. Be good.
What's the mission? Fighting again?
No, not fighting.
Just going down to the village.
I'll be back soon.
Let's eat first.
Muah.
Let's eat.
No kissing, Eat.
So sweet.
What's this?
This is what eating is.
The food is here.
Here.
Kisses won't fill you up, but food will.
It won't.
Still not full?
Are you full yet?
I'm full.
But I'm not.
I'm not full yet.
Eat your food. Stop kissing me.
Hey!
Get up! I said get up! Get up!
Ouch!